<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
  <title>Mailpile: The Mailpile Blog</title>
  <link>https://www.mailpile.is/blog/</link>
  <item>
    <title>Progress Report: events, packages, 1.0</title>
    <link>https://www.mailpile.is/blog/2018-10-27_Progress_Report.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello world! How are you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m writing this, sitting on a bus in Luxembourg, realizing that we have been
very quite for quite some time. Our last posts were in May, first a report on
&lt;a href=&#34;2018-05-03_Desktop_Usability_Tests.html&#34;&gt;the results of our first round of desktop package usability
testing&lt;/a&gt;, quickly followed by a
&lt;a href=&#34;2018-05-14_PGP_Security_Alert.html&#34;&gt;statement on how the EFail flaw impacted
Mailpile&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then we may have been quiet, but we have not been idle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;square&#34;&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Many, many bugs have been found and fixed
 &lt;li&gt;The first round of our desktop packaging project is complete,
     we have packages and very basic desktop integration for both
     Windows and the Mac
 &lt;li&gt;Mailpile&#39;s multi-user Apache integration
     (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/tree/master/shared-data/multipile&#34;
         target=_blank&gt;Multipile&lt;/a&gt;)
     has been simplified and reworked
 &lt;li&gt;Mailpile&#39;s internal (in-memory) master security key is now
     protected against memory corruption
 &lt;li&gt;Mailpile is now &lt;i&gt;compatible&lt;/i&gt; with
     &lt;a target=_blank href=&#34;https://autocrypt.org/&#34;&gt;Autocrypt Level 1&lt;/a&gt;,
     but not yet fully compliant
 &lt;li&gt;I attended the OpenPGP e-mail summit in Brussels
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to publicly thank Alex and Pétur for their hard work on the
Mailpile Desktop packages, and in particular for how they took delays and slow
responses from my end graciously and in stride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read on to learn a bit more about the OpenPGP E-mail Summit, our CCC plans, the
state of the desktop packaging work, and of course the elusive 1.0 release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The OpenPGP Summit and 35c3&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last weekend I visited the &lt;a href=&#34;https://mailfence.com/&#34;&gt;Mailfence&lt;/a&gt; office in
Brussels, to attend the annual OpenPGP E-mail Summit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The OpenPGP E-mail Summit is one of my favourite community events. Just
two days long, it is an informal event focused on getting people from
the world of e-mail encryption to exchange knowledge and collaborate. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year there were (by my rough guesstimate) about 50 people from over
20 projects present, including Phil Zimmermann himself, the creator of
PGP. I was very happy to meet him and shake his hand. We ended up having
about 20 different sessions, discussing topics ranging from key server
management, to user interfaces, to updating the OpenPGP standard itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.gnupg.org/EmailSummit2018Notes&#34;&gt;Notes from all the sessions have been published.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was also a dinner and plenty of socializing, the value of which is
not to be understated. Meeting people face-to-face almost always makes
collaboration online easier and more productive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Mailpile, the main outcomes of the summit were the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There seems to be potential for partnerships with 2-3 other businesses in
      the OpenPGP space, which we look forward to exploring further.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Web Key Directory specification is still evolving in ways which may
      require we re-evaluate how we use it in Mailpile.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mailpile will aim for Autocrypt Level 1 compliance, soon! Our aim is to
      get a member of the community to review and confirm our implementation
      at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://events.ccc.de/2018/09/11/35c3-call-for-participation-and-submission-guidelines/&#34;&gt;35c3&lt;/a&gt;
      conference. We have a volunteer to perform the review.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have a vouncher and will be representing Mailpile at 35c3. Come say hi!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a productive weekend!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;When will Mac and Windows packages be available?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ve e-mailed me asking this question; my apologies for not
answering. I haven&#39;t replied, because I don&#39;t know! If I did, our
download package would just say so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three main tasks we need to complete before we make the
desktop packages available to the wider Internet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A short private beta, to reassure ourselves the packages
      don&#39;t have any blindingly obvious bugs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Launch a Discourse forum, so our users have a venue to help
      each other out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finish our &#34;build robot&#34; so packaging becomes an automated
      process without any human bottlenecks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not going to commit to a time-line for getting this done, but this
work is are all in progress and won&#39;t take forever. This year? This
year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s worth mentioning that some important tasks have been postponed and
will not be blocking the availability of packages - so these packages
will not be &#34;Mailpile 1.0&#34;. But they&#39;re close.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So, what about Mailpile 1.0?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our current release is 1.0.0rc4, tagged and pushed earlier today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At times it feels like we&#39;re chasing &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zeno%27s_paradoxes#Achilles_and_the_tortoise&#34;&gt;the tortoise from one of Zeno&#39;s
paradoxes&lt;/a&gt;,
always getting closer but never able to catch up. For every issue we
close, others are opened...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in spite of that, my to-do list for the elusive &#34;Mailpile 1.0&#34;
release really is starting to get shorter and the issues that remain are
not as complex as the ones we&#39;ve resolved. I&#39;ve updated the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/milestone/4&#34;&gt;GitHub
Milestone&lt;/a&gt; to reflect
the current priority issues. It&#39;s not a long list, mostly relatively
minor bugfixes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two big items left on my 1.0 roadmap are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fully implement Autocrypt Level 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implement easy remote access (PageKite and Tor Hidden Services)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The former is necessary for an interoperable and complete implementation
of &#34;PGP for everyone&#34;, and the latter is needed so people can access
their Mailpiles remotely - in particular to access their Mailpile from
their smart-phones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, I&#39;m not going to make any promises about when these will get
done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this mini roadmap is still worth sharing, because if you liked the
vision behind Mailpile and those two issues aren&#39;t critical for your
use-case... then maybe Mailpile is already ready for you. Maybe!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One-point-oh is an important label, but it&#39;s not everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mailpile is already a great e-mail client. Give it a try!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>PGP Security Alert</title>
    <link>https://www.mailpile.is/blog/2018-05-14_PGP_Security_Alert.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Mailpile users,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2018/05/attention-pgp-users-new-vulnerabilities-require-you-take-action-now&#34;&gt;EFF have publicized advice from a group of security
researchers&lt;/a&gt;,
who claim there is a serious problem with PGP encrypted e-mail. Users
are advised to disable automatic decryption of e-mail and exercise
caution or avoid decrypting e-mails entirely until the vulnerabilities
have been addressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Second (and 3rd) Update&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The actual &lt;a href=&#34;https://efail.de/&#34;&gt;research is now public&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell, Mailpile is [mostly] not vulnerable to these flaws and
the table of tested mail clients in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://efail.de/efail-attack-paper.pdf&#34;&gt;the paper itself&lt;/a&gt; is misleading
in that regard. This is unfortunate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some exceptions though, see below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Why is Mailpile [mostly] not vulnerable?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of defense in depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mailpile does not display HTML content by default&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Before displaying HTML, Mailpile cleans up malformed and incomplete tags.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When displaying HTML, Mailpile does not load remote content by default.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mailpile respects the GnuPG error messages which warn of invalid data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mailpile never sends auto-replies to incoming mail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The direct exfiltration attack is completely thwarted by #2, and would be
mitigated in any case by #1, #3 and #5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The CBC/CFB Gadget Attack is mostly thwarted by #4, and would also be
mitigated in any case by #1, #3 and #5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell, most Mailpile users will not be vulnerable to
EFail. Don&#39;t let the red mark in the PDF deceive you! Also, it&#39;s worth
mentioning that this isn&#39;t a lucky accident - this is a direct
validation of how we approach security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of that approach is simply taking these things seriously. If anyone
disagrees with my analysis or finds other flaws in Mailpile, we want to know
about it and will do our best to remedy things as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Wait.. mostly? When is Mailpile vulnerable?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mailpile is vulnerable to the CBC/CFB Gadget Attack in the following
cases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Something is obsolete, either:&lt;ol&gt;
   &lt;li&gt;Mailpile is configured to use an out-of-date version of GnuPG, or
   &lt;li&gt;The encrypted data being exfiltrated is so old that GnuPG doesn&#39;t
       expect and require it to have a Modification Detection Code (MDC).
   &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And:&lt;ol&gt;
   &lt;li&gt;The user manually displays HTML and loads remote images, or
   &lt;li&gt;The user has previously enabled HTML and images for the sender
   &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In practical terms, this means even if you are running up-to-date
software, then old content (messages that are 10-20 years old, or more)
could potentially be stolen - but only with a bit of social engineering,
and only if you still have the keys on your keychain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The risk is more serious if you have configured Mailpile to use an
obsolete version of GnuPG - use of GnuPG 1.4.x is still relatively
common, and our tests suggest it is probably vulnerable. In this case
more recent messages may be at risk, but the social engineering is still
required for attacks to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fixes addressing both of these attack vectors have been pushed to our
GitHub repository and will be included in our next release candidate.
They are already present in our &lt;a href=&#34;/download/linux.html&#34;&gt;nightly Debian packages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;First Update&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further details have emerged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Werner, the lead developer of GnuPG, &lt;a href=&#34;https://lists.gnupg.org/pipermail/gnupg-users/2018-May/060315.html&#34;&gt;claims that the flaw has to do
with an interaction between HTML mail and GnuPG error handling in common
e-mail clients and PGP
plugins&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this is indeed the case, most Mailpile users are not vulnerable since
HTML messages are not rendered by default - and even when HTML is
rendered, loading of images and other remote assets are also disabled by
default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would rather take the EFF&#39;s advice, in spite of Werner&#39;s update,
our original advice is included below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Disabling Automatic Decryption&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This advice is obsolete! It is preserved here for historic reasons.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within Mailpile, the way to disable automatic decryption is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the web interface, visit the &lt;strong&gt;Settings&lt;/strong&gt; page&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the &lt;strong&gt;CLI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run the following command: &lt;code&gt;set prefs.index_encrypted = false&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will disable automatic decryption of incoming mail. However, manual
decryption (decryption when messages are read) will still work and it is
advisable to not read any encrypted mail until we know more about the
attack and whether Mailpile is actually vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you &lt;strong&gt;absolutely must read encrypted e-mail&lt;/strong&gt;, we recommend taking
your computer offline before doing so, so as to prevent network-based
side channels from leaking sensitive key material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To re-enable indexing of encrypted messages, perform the same steps
again, except &lt;code&gt;set prefs.index_encrypted = true&lt;/code&gt; at the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is going on?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What follows is idle speculation. Please take it with an appropriately
sized grain of salt!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-decoration: line-through&#34;&gt;

I don&#39;t know what is going on. However, I trust the EFF. They would not
be advising we disable such an important tool unless it was of critical
importance.

The implications of the advisory, are that automatic e-mail decryption
can leak details of your private key material back to a malicious
attacker.

The mechanism is unknown, but the common denominator in the EFF&#39;s list
of vulnerable e-mail clients is use of GnuPG - which Mailpile also
relies upon.

My guess, is that there is a flaw in GnuPG which allows attackers to
craft encrypted messages that force GnuPG to leak key material back over
the network to an attacker.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See updates from myself and Werner above. The situation is not as bad as
it first appeared - in fact, it appears Mailpile is not vulnerable to this
problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the same, because we take these things seriously, I have filed issues
in our issue tracker for follow-up work and proactive improvements:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/issues/2072&#34;&gt;#2072&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/issues/2073&#34;&gt;#2073&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/issues/2074&#34;&gt;#2074&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/issues/2075&#34;&gt;#2075&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/issues/2077&#34;&gt;#2077&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will post updates as more information becomes available.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Desktop Usability Tests</title>
    <link>https://www.mailpile.is/blog/2018-05-03_Desktop_Usability_Tests.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week was exciting!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mailpile desktop platform team got together for a miniature
developer summit in Reykjavík, Iceland. Alex, Pétur and myself all flew
in from our corners of the globe, and Oktavía welcomed us and made sure
everything went as smoothly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We spent some time working at Stofan, my favourite café, and some
time hanging out at the offices of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.1984.is/&#34;&gt;1984&lt;/a&gt;, who
graciously lent us desks and a meeting room. Thank you, 1984!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was really nice to have the whole team together in one place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We ate some traditional Icelandic food, tasted some Icelandic
hipster-beer, chatted and just gelled a bit as a team. I got a chance to
give everyone a bit more insight into Mailpile&#39;s background, discussing
everything from
&lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013-09-05_PayPal_Freezes_Campaign_Funds.html&#34;&gt;PayPal freezing our funds&lt;/a&gt; to
&lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2014-10-07_Some_Thoughts_on_GnuPG.html&#34;&gt;GnuPG integration challenges&lt;/a&gt; to
&lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2015-05-18_Digging_for_Data.html&#34;&gt;extracting spreadsheets from e-mail&lt;/a&gt;
to introducing &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2015-09-22_pyConUK_and_Mailpile_Mel.html&#34;&gt;Mailpile Mel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main event though, was to get a bunch of helpful humans to come test
the Mailpile installers and desktop integration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usability testing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/files/2018-04-Mailpile-Desktop-Usability.jpg&#34; border=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why usability test?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more familiar you are with something, the harder it can be to see it
clearly. You see what you expect to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In software, this means software developers quickly become blind to the
flaws of their own code. We literally cannot see them! Getting a fresh
pair of eyes is invaluable, especially if you are interested in
understanding which parts of an interface are confusing or unclear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To compound matters even further, everyone uses their computer in a
slightly different way. The way I use Mailpile may work perfectly, but
if you do things in a different order, use a different mail server, run
on a different version of Linux ... any of those differences may trigger
a poorly tested code path and uncover a bug.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usability tests can be as simple as asking a friend to try your thing
and just watching how they do and taking notes. It doesn&#39;t have to be
complicated to provide value and I encourage all software developers
to just grab a pen and some paper and watch people use their stuff. You
always learn something!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our case, we had some quite specific goals, so we were a little bit
more methodical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How we tested, and why&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this round of tests, these were our main goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To verify that our draft installers actually work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To check whether the software &#34;makes sense&#34; to a new user.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first goal ws relatively straightforward, technical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latter was much more subtle, and relates to the fact that Mailpile is quite
complex and in many ways unusual software. The general public is not used to
running servers on their computers - Mailpile is a web server. The general
public is not used to interacting with local software using a web browser - but
that&#39;s how Mailpile works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, our installation sequence and the initial setup process needs
to gradually introduce these concepts. We wanted to get a feel for whether
it was actually succeeding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oktavía scheduled and recruited a moderately diverse group of volunteers
to come test. All told we had 3 men and 3 women, of mixed ages. Some were
Windows users, others Mac users. They were all tech-savvy enough to own
their own laptops, but not necessarily programmers themselves. Some
digital natives, some less so. Roughly our target demographic for our next
release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The structure of the test itself was relatively simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We tested with one volunteer at a time. Each time we started with
introductions, explaining roughly what Mailpile was and what we expected
of our volunteers. We warned them we wouldn&#39;t help them much, asked them
to think out loud if they could. Made sure they understood that failures
and problems were &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;, that breaking things would help us identify
things to fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, each person was given a USB stick with an installer on it and
instructions to attempt to install Mailpile and go through the initial
setup until we told them to stop. Once stopped, they were to exit and shut
down the app. We watched over their shoulder and made notes. We tried to
resist the urge to answer any questions, to see if they could figure
things out themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally Oktavia asked a few questions about the experience, we thanked
them, gave them stickers and chocolate and sent them on their way!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Easy, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What we learned&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even a simple, short test like this has many potential pitfalls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does the installer work?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does the app run?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does the tester successfully navigate from the installer to the app,
    and from the app to the browser?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does the tester understand that shutting down Mailpile and logging out
    from the web UI are not the same things?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is the process confusing or uncomfortable?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the answer to any of these questions is &#34;no&#34;, then we would like to
understand &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;, so we can fix the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answers in this case were mostly good news! Which is refreshing,
since last time we tested Mailpile in this environment, the result was
so many failures and so much confusion that we went back to the drawing
board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found some minor bugs, but everyone managed to install the app and
complete the first stage of the test. Good news! Nobody was frustrated,
most confusion was minor. Also good news!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shutting down the app was the main failure; most of our participants
thought they were done when they had logged out of the web interface.
But, we have ways to address this. And worst-case, we need to make sure
Mailpile shuts down cleanly when the computer powers down anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To sum up the main lessons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The installers work!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The app runs!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People didn&#39;t read the text in the GUI: less is probably more here&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Windows users expect the installer to launch the app when done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our Mac build process created a broken GnuPG&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our Mac build was launching the in-browser UI prematurely&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our desktop notifications on the Mac were spammy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The logged-out page should explain that the app is still running&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nobody notices systray or status bar icons on first run&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our testers were comfortable and happy, most chose to keep the
     app installed so they could play more at home.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We learned a lot!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watching people use the app and interact with our work was very
stimulating. The next day we had a (somewhat hung over) brainstorming
session, discussing how things could be different or better. In the end we
felt comfortable continuing with a mostly unchanged design. The issues
were mostly minor and felt fixable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we&#39;re on track! The next step will be to fix the bugs and get some
&#34;alpha&#34; packages ready for wider testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exciting!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 03 May 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Building up Steam</title>
    <link>https://www.mailpile.is/blog/2018-03-29_Building_up_Steam.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Wow, we&#39;ve been so busy making progress we forgot to let you all know
how we are progressing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, Mailpile in 2018 has been all about building up steam for the
Mailpile train! We hired me (or rather – Bjarni hired me!) and I have
been working on project management and thinking towards the future,
including human resource work (I spent a lot of time looking to lessons
learned on diverse and inclusive hiring practices). This has resulted in
the hiring of two more persons – &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alexander and Pétur who, along side Bjarni and myself, will be taking
Mailpile to as many users as possible!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who are these new additions to the Mailpile Team? Well, Alex Haase is a
self-proclaimed generalist, who has a background spanning kernel modules
to javascript, bare metal to Windows. He lurrvvs tinkering on Open
Source side projects and refereeing Roller Derby when he‘s not
Mailpiling. Pétur is all about high level software engineering.
Specifically modelling and automatic programming. He loves collaborative
design by prototyping, designing and exploring new ideas using scissors,
papers, glue and different shades of colour. His favorite movie quote?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&#34;It&#39;s a UNIX system.&#34; — Jurrasic Park :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What will they be doing with us? We&#39;re glad you asked! Their main tasks
relate to packaging Mailpile for the Mac and Windows platforms, and in
doing so making Mailpile more accessible to more people! Hooray!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contracts were signed in mid-March and we are on track to deliver
packages and an improved native user experience within 3-4 months. So
soon, soon, at long last, &lt;a href=&#34;/download/&#34;&gt;our downloads page&lt;/a&gt; won&#39;t tell
people our packages are being reworked.  IT will tell people to go forth
and install what Alex and Pétur have built!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are now well settled in our virtual working space, as our physical
selves are spread over Europe and the US. We would love a visit, so
please come by the Mailpile IRC - #mailpile (Freenode, or
&lt;a href=&#34;https://riot.im/app/#/room/#freenode_#mailpile:matrix.org&#34;&gt;Riot&lt;/a&gt;),
but bring your own coffee!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 29 Mar 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>We are Hiring!</title>
    <link>https://www.mailpile.is/blog/2018-01-22_We_are_Hiring.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Good news!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have secured funding, hired Oktavía to manage things and posted ads for
the first positions we would like to fill: Windows and Mac OS developers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/jobs/&#34;&gt;Details are on our jobs page.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please spread the word!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
</channel></rss>