<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
  <title>Mailpile: The Mailpile Blog</title>
  <link>https://www.mailpile.is/blog/</link>
  <item>
    <title>CCCamp19 and further EFail mitigations</title>
    <link>https://www.mailpile.is/blog/2019-08-31_CCCamp_EFail.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello world!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I write this, I have mostly recovered from the amazing Chaos
Communication Camp in Germany. I attended the camp mostly as a holiday,
but there were of course quite a few Mailpile related discussions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most interesting of those related to EFail. I spent a couple of
afternoons sitting in the shade with researchers and developers who
work on OpenPGP related things. We discussed &lt;a href=&#34;https://efail.de/&#34;&gt;EFail&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those of you who haven&#39;t heard of EFail, it was one of the most
serious vulnerabilities the OpenPGP community has ever had to deal with:
by combining flaws in e-mail clients with flaws in legacy PGP (and
S/MIME) implementations, EFail described multiple ways an attacker could
turn a vulnerable e-mail client into a decryption oracle and steal the
cleartext of previously secured communications. Cryptosystem flaws don&#39;t
get much worse than that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was such a serious issue that the EFF recommended people disable
PGP entirely, at least for a little while. This triggered a rather
emotional backlash from the PGP community, and unfortunately a lot of
misinformation and misunderstandings were published. Some of which
still have not been corrected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a community, we&#39;re still coming to terms with some of the
implications. Those of us who aren&#39;t in denial (which is disturbingly
common) are still mulling over ways to secure our tools and defend
against similar flaws in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have written before about &lt;a href=&#34;2018-05-14_PGP_Security_Alert.html&#34;&gt;Mailpile and
EFail&lt;/a&gt;: there were a few issues that
needed fixing, but overall Mailpile weathered EFail relatively well.
Exfiltrating cleartext from Mailpile was possible, but it was not fully
automated and required social engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The social engineering aspects are still quite serious, and some are
easier to exploit than others. The most trivial EFail exploit is to
send someone a message they&#39;re likely to reply to, with the ciphertext
you want to exfiltrate appended to the end after a long boring
boilerplate signature or quoted message. If the mail client decrypts,
and the recipient replies without reading and pruning their response...
hey presto, you&#39;ve exfiltratrated the secret message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the outcomes of these discussions at camp, were some concrete
recommendations on how Mailpile could make such social engineering less
likely to succeed. The guiding principle I ended up with, was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the user is probably not going to see the content, do not decrypt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the plane home from Germany, I implemented this strategy. So for the
first time, Mailpile will deliberately decline to decrypt parts of
incoming e-mail, if the message structure is such that it might might
provide cover for EFail social engineering attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The change wasn&#39;t huge, but the security impact is significant. We
welcome any and all feedback: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/commit/79551b17928a9f990ac5e1336386caab8b183323&#34;&gt;the code is here&lt;/a&gt;.
This patch is already in &lt;a href=&#34;/download/linux.html&#34;&gt;the nightly packages&lt;/a&gt;
and will hit the release branch next time I update it - which should be
soon, we&#39;ve got quite a few important fixes queued up by now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://sebastian-schinzel.de/&#34;&gt;Sebastian&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/valodim&#34;&gt;Vincent&lt;/a&gt; for helping me figure out how to
improve Mailpile on this front. And thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ccc.de/&#34;&gt;CCC&lt;/a&gt;
for providing venues for these conversations to take place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please feel free to &lt;a href=&#34;https://community.mailpile.is/t/blog-post-about-cccamp-19-and-efail/243&#34;&gt;discuss this post in our Community
Forum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2019 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Burned Out and Happy?</title>
    <link>https://www.mailpile.is/blog/2019-04-06_Burnout.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Mailpile Users and Backers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just wanted to post a short note, to explain why development has been
so slow for the last year - or longer. The long and the short of it is,
I&#39;m burned out, and this has been the case for quite some time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I care deeply about this project, but it really is too big for one
person and I haven&#39;t successfully built a team to support me. That&#39;s not
to discount the contributions and efforts of our community, but at the
end of the day I&#39;ve been the one responsible for keeping the ball
rolling. I review the pull requests, I respond to issues, I file the tax
returns, I try to spend your donations wisely... and I write most of the
code. Doing this well is a lot of work!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This responsibility, combined with frustration over how slow progress
has been, has really worn me down. When I&#39;m feeling down, I&#39;m not very
productive, leading to a vicious cycle of feeling bad about a the lack
of progress and then becoming incapable of making progress as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s not good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took me a while to realize what was going on, to realize I was burned
out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also a money dimension here; although I cannot say thank you
enough for all the donations and support from our community, the fact is
that Mailpile has not been able to pay me a decent wage for my work,
&lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt;. I know my value on the job market, and I&#39;ve been underpaid since
day one. That was my choice and I don&#39;t regret it; but it&#39;s still become
harder and harder for me to justify. I have a family now and I&#39;ve
drained most of my savings trying to get 1.0 out the door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I&#39;m giving myself a break and focusing on other things for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve gotten a (part-time) job working with the fine folks at
&lt;a href=&#34;https://isnic.is/&#34;&gt;ISNIC&lt;/a&gt;, I&#39;m working out regularly at the pool and
I&#39;m spending more time with friends and family. &lt;em&gt;Life is good!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I&#39;ve accepted and embraced my burnout, I&#39;m actually feeling
pretty happy.  Identifying a problem is the first step towards a
resolution, and I&#39;m already well on my way with steps two and three.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to be 100% clear: &lt;strong&gt;Mailpile is not dead!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Far from it, I&#39;m way too proud of this app to just walk away and let it
die. But for now, Mailpile has been demoted to a part time job at most,
and a beloved hobby at worst. Considering how unproductive I had become,
you may not even notice any difference...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, if reading this gives you the urge to help out, here are a few
things you can do for me and for Mailpile:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/download/&#34;&gt;Use Mailpile&lt;/a&gt;! It&#39;s not perfect, but it&#39;s pretty great.
&lt;li&gt;Tweet or &lt;a href=&#34;https://joinmastodon.org/&#34;&gt;toot&lt;/a&gt; what you like about it...
    I&#39;m listening!
&lt;li&gt;Help make our &lt;a href=&#34;https://community.mailpile.is/categories&#34;&gt;Community Discourse&lt;/a&gt;
    a useful, welcoming place.
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/donate/&#34;&gt;Donate&lt;/a&gt;: As always, I&#39;ll do my best to spend it wisely.
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-- Bjarni&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2019 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Community Discourse: Launched!</title>
    <link>https://www.mailpile.is/blog/2019-02-15_Community_Discourse.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello Mailpile world!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have launched a new site for community discussions about Mailpile:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://community.mailpile.is/categories&#34;&gt;community.mailpile.is&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The site runs the excellent &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.discourse.org/&#34;&gt;Discourse&lt;/a&gt; software,
which means it&#39;s primarily an accessible web-based discussion forum, but it can
also be used as a mailing list for those who prefer such things. Our Discourse
was set up by a kind member of our community, &lt;b&gt;Greg Sutcliffe&lt;/b&gt;. Thanks
Greg! And thanks &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/asta_fish&#34;&gt;Ásta&lt;/a&gt; for helping me launch
the site properly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the site is to give people a searchable, &#34;on the record&#34; venue to
&lt;a href=&#34;https://community.mailpile.is/c/uncategorized&#34;&gt;discuss Mailpile, provide feedback, exchange tips and
tricks&lt;/a&gt; - and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://community.mailpile.is/c/support&#34;&gt;get support&lt;/a&gt;. The forum is brand new and
pretty empty at the moment, so please feel free to post something and start a
conversation!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more ephemeral discussions, we still have
&lt;a href=&#34;https://webchat.freenode.net/?channels=%23mailpile&amp;amp;uio=d4&#34;&gt;#mailpile on Freenode&lt;/a&gt;,
and for bug reports we have
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/issues&#34;&gt;GitHub Issues&lt;/a&gt;. The Community site
is for everything else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Including &lt;a href=&#34;https://community.mailpile.is/t/community-discourse-launched/31&#34;&gt;discussions about our blog
posts!&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Progress Report: events, packages, 1.0</title>
    <link>https://www.mailpile.is/blog/2018-10-27_Progress_Report.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello world! How are you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m writing this, sitting on a bus in Luxembourg, realizing that we have
been very quiet for quite some time. Our last posts were in May, first a
report on &lt;a href=&#34;2018-05-03_Desktop_Usability_Tests.html&#34;&gt;the results of our first round of desktop package usability
testing&lt;/a&gt;, quickly followed by a
&lt;a href=&#34;2018-05-14_PGP_Security_Alert.html&#34;&gt;statement on how the EFail flaw impacted
Mailpile&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then we may have been quiet, but we have not been idle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;square&#34;&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Many, many bugs have been found and fixed
 &lt;li&gt;The first round of our desktop packaging project is complete,
     we have packages and very basic desktop integration for both
     Windows and the Mac
 &lt;li&gt;Mailpile&#39;s multi-user Apache integration
     (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/tree/master/shared-data/multipile&#34;
         target=_blank&gt;Multipile&lt;/a&gt;)
     has been simplified and reworked
 &lt;li&gt;Mailpile&#39;s internal (in-memory) master security key is now
     protected against memory corruption
 &lt;li&gt;Mailpile is now &lt;i&gt;compatible&lt;/i&gt; with
     &lt;a target=_blank href=&#34;https://autocrypt.org/&#34;&gt;Autocrypt Level 1&lt;/a&gt;,
     but not yet fully compliant
 &lt;li&gt;I attended the OpenPGP e-mail summit in Brussels
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to publicly thank Alex and Pétur for their hard work on the
Mailpile Desktop packages, and in particular for how they took delays and slow
responses from my end graciously and in stride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read on to learn a bit more about the OpenPGP E-mail Summit, our CCC plans, the
state of the desktop packaging work, and of course the elusive 1.0 release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The OpenPGP Summit and 35c3&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last weekend I visited the &lt;a href=&#34;https://mailfence.com/&#34;&gt;Mailfence&lt;/a&gt; office in
Brussels, to attend the annual OpenPGP E-mail Summit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The OpenPGP E-mail Summit is one of my favourite community events. Just
two days long, it is an informal event focused on getting people from
the world of e-mail encryption to exchange knowledge and collaborate. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year there were (by my rough guesstimate) about 50 people from over
20 projects present, including Phil Zimmermann himself, the creator of
PGP. I was very happy to meet him and shake his hand. We ended up having
about 20 different sessions, discussing topics ranging from key server
management, to user interfaces, to updating the OpenPGP standard itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.gnupg.org/EmailSummit2018Notes&#34;&gt;Notes from all the sessions have been published.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was also a dinner and plenty of socializing, the value of which is
not to be understated. Meeting people face-to-face almost always makes
collaboration online easier and more productive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Mailpile, the main outcomes of the summit were the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There seems to be potential for partnerships with 2-3 other businesses in
      the OpenPGP space, which we look forward to exploring further.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Web Key Directory specification is still evolving in ways which may
      require we re-evaluate how we use it in Mailpile.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mailpile will aim for Autocrypt Level 1 compliance, soon! Our aim is to
      get a member of the community to review and confirm our implementation
      at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://events.ccc.de/2018/09/11/35c3-call-for-participation-and-submission-guidelines/&#34;&gt;35c3&lt;/a&gt;
      conference. We have a volunteer to perform the review.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have a voucher and will be representing Mailpile at 35c3. Come say hi!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a productive weekend!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;When will Mac and Windows packages be available?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ve e-mailed me asking this question; my apologies for not
answering. I haven&#39;t replied, because I don&#39;t know! If I did, our
download page would just say so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three main tasks we need to complete before we make the
desktop packages available to the wider Internet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A short private beta, to reassure ourselves the packages
      don&#39;t have any blindingly obvious bugs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Launch a Discourse forum, so our users have a venue to help
      each other out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finish our &#34;build robot&#34; so packaging becomes an automated
      process without any human bottlenecks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not going to commit to a time-line for getting this done, but this
work is all in progress and won&#39;t take forever. This year? This year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s worth mentioning that some important tasks have been postponed and
will not be blocking the availability of packages - so these packages
will not be &#34;Mailpile 1.0&#34;. But they&#39;re close.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So, what about Mailpile 1.0?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our current release is 1.0.0rc4, tagged and pushed earlier today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At times it feels like we&#39;re chasing &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zeno%27s_paradoxes#Achilles_and_the_tortoise&#34;&gt;the tortoise from one of Zeno&#39;s
paradoxes&lt;/a&gt;,
always getting closer but never able to catch up. For every issue we
close, others are opened...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in spite of that, my to-do list for the elusive &#34;Mailpile 1.0&#34;
release really is starting to get shorter and the issues that remain are
not as complex as the ones we&#39;ve resolved. I&#39;ve updated the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/milestone/4&#34;&gt;GitHub
Milestone&lt;/a&gt; to reflect
the current priority issues. It&#39;s not a long list, mostly relatively
minor bugfixes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two big items left on my 1.0 roadmap are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fully implement Autocrypt Level 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implement easy remote access (PageKite and Tor Hidden Services)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The former is necessary for an interoperable and complete implementation
of &#34;PGP for everyone&#34;, and the latter is needed so people can access
their Mailpiles remotely - in particular to access their Mailpile from
their smart-phones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, I&#39;m not going to make any promises about when these will get
done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this mini roadmap is still worth sharing, because if you liked the
vision behind Mailpile and those two issues aren&#39;t critical for your
use-case... then maybe Mailpile is already ready for you. Maybe!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One-point-oh is an important label, but it&#39;s not everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mailpile is already a great e-mail client. Give it a try!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>PGP Security Alert</title>
    <link>https://www.mailpile.is/blog/2018-05-14_PGP_Security_Alert.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Mailpile users,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2018/05/attention-pgp-users-new-vulnerabilities-require-you-take-action-now&#34;&gt;EFF have publicized advice from a group of security
researchers&lt;/a&gt;,
who claim there is a serious problem with PGP encrypted e-mail. Users
are advised to disable automatic decryption of e-mail and exercise
caution or avoid decrypting e-mails entirely until the vulnerabilities
have been addressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Second (and 3rd) Update&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The actual &lt;a href=&#34;https://efail.de/&#34;&gt;research is now public&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell, Mailpile is [mostly] not vulnerable to these flaws and
the table of tested mail clients in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://efail.de/efail-attack-paper.pdf&#34;&gt;the paper itself&lt;/a&gt; is misleading
in that regard. This is unfortunate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some exceptions though, see below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Why is Mailpile [mostly] not vulnerable?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of defense in depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mailpile does not display HTML content by default&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Before displaying HTML, Mailpile cleans up malformed and incomplete tags.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When displaying HTML, Mailpile does not load remote content by default.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mailpile respects the GnuPG error messages which warn of invalid data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mailpile never sends auto-replies to incoming mail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The direct exfiltration attack is completely thwarted by #2, and would be
mitigated in any case by #1, #3 and #5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The CBC/CFB Gadget Attack is mostly thwarted by #4, and would also be
mitigated in any case by #1, #3 and #5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell, most Mailpile users will not be vulnerable to
EFail. Don&#39;t let the red mark in the PDF deceive you! Also, it&#39;s worth
mentioning that this isn&#39;t a lucky accident - this is a direct
validation of how we approach security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of that approach is simply taking these things seriously. If anyone
disagrees with my analysis or finds other flaws in Mailpile, we want to know
about it and will do our best to remedy things as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Wait.. mostly? When is Mailpile vulnerable?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mailpile is vulnerable to the CBC/CFB Gadget Attack in the following
cases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Something is obsolete, either:&lt;ol&gt;
   &lt;li&gt;Mailpile is configured to use an out-of-date version of GnuPG, or
   &lt;li&gt;The encrypted data being exfiltrated is so old that GnuPG doesn&#39;t
       expect and require it to have a Modification Detection Code (MDC).
   &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And:&lt;ol&gt;
   &lt;li&gt;The user manually displays HTML and loads remote images, or
   &lt;li&gt;The user has previously enabled HTML and images for the sender
   &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In practical terms, this means even if you are running up-to-date
software, then old content (messages that are 10-20 years old, or more)
could potentially be stolen - but only with a bit of social engineering,
and only if you still have the keys on your keychain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The risk is more serious if you have configured Mailpile to use an
obsolete version of GnuPG - use of GnuPG 1.4.x is still relatively
common, and our tests suggest it is probably vulnerable. In this case
more recent messages may be at risk, but the social engineering is still
required for attacks to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fixes addressing both of these attack vectors have been pushed to our
GitHub repository and will be included in our next release candidate.
They are already present in our &lt;a href=&#34;/download/linux.html&#34;&gt;nightly Debian packages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;First Update&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further details have emerged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Werner, the lead developer of GnuPG, &lt;a href=&#34;https://lists.gnupg.org/pipermail/gnupg-users/2018-May/060315.html&#34;&gt;claims that the flaw has to do
with an interaction between HTML mail and GnuPG error handling in common
e-mail clients and PGP
plugins&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this is indeed the case, most Mailpile users are not vulnerable since
HTML messages are not rendered by default - and even when HTML is
rendered, loading of images and other remote assets are also disabled by
default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would rather take the EFF&#39;s advice, in spite of Werner&#39;s update,
our original advice is included below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Disabling Automatic Decryption&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This advice is obsolete! It is preserved here for historic reasons.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within Mailpile, the way to disable automatic decryption is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the web interface, visit the &lt;strong&gt;Settings&lt;/strong&gt; page&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the &lt;strong&gt;CLI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run the following command: &lt;code&gt;set prefs.index_encrypted = false&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will disable automatic decryption of incoming mail. However, manual
decryption (decryption when messages are read) will still work and it is
advisable to not read any encrypted mail until we know more about the
attack and whether Mailpile is actually vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you &lt;strong&gt;absolutely must read encrypted e-mail&lt;/strong&gt;, we recommend taking
your computer offline before doing so, so as to prevent network-based
side channels from leaking sensitive key material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To re-enable indexing of encrypted messages, perform the same steps
again, except &lt;code&gt;set prefs.index_encrypted = true&lt;/code&gt; at the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is going on?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What follows is idle speculation. Please take it with an appropriately
sized grain of salt!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-decoration: line-through&#34;&gt;

I don&#39;t know what is going on. However, I trust the EFF. They would not
be advising we disable such an important tool unless it was of critical
importance.

The implications of the advisory, are that automatic e-mail decryption
can leak details of your private key material back to a malicious
attacker.

The mechanism is unknown, but the common denominator in the EFF&#39;s list
of vulnerable e-mail clients is use of GnuPG - which Mailpile also
relies upon.

My guess, is that there is a flaw in GnuPG which allows attackers to
craft encrypted messages that force GnuPG to leak key material back over
the network to an attacker.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See updates from myself and Werner above. The situation is not as bad as
it first appeared - in fact, it appears Mailpile is not vulnerable to this
problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the same, because we take these things seriously, I have filed issues
in our issue tracker for follow-up work and proactive improvements:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/issues/2072&#34;&gt;#2072&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/issues/2073&#34;&gt;#2073&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/issues/2074&#34;&gt;#2074&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/issues/2075&#34;&gt;#2075&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/issues/2077&#34;&gt;#2077&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will post updates as more information becomes available.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
</channel></rss>