<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
  <title>Mailpile: The Mailpile Blog</title>
  <link>http://www.mailpile.is/blog/</link>
  <item>
    <title>Beta III preparations</title>
    <link>http://www.mailpile.is/blog/2015-07-07_Beta_III_prep.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week&#39;s big news was of course &lt;a href=&#34;2015-07-02_Licensing_Decision.html&#34;&gt;the licensing
decision&lt;/a&gt; - the vote completed and the
project&#39;s license is now officially the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gnu.org/licenses/agpl-3.0.en.html&#34;&gt;GNU Affero General Public
License&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vote was very close, but the slight majority from the community reflects
both the wishes of the original project founders and matches the political
goals of the project itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks again to everyone who voted!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the technical front, it was a slow week. I spent some time reflecting on the
original road-map and decided to make one major change to the Beta III plans:
the &#34;Fast Startup&#34; milestone will be postponed until later this summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason for this change is that although the code appears to work, it got
done too late to get reviewed by any 3rd parties. For many other aspects of
Mailpile that would be OK, but our encrypted on-disk storage is a bit different.
It&#39;s both difficult and error prone to change storage formats after the fact,
so it is of particular importance to get this done right the first time around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delaying Beta III is also not an option, because I need feedback on the
usability of all the new setup interfaces and composer improvements so the
worst problems can be fixed before 1.0.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This decision scuppered most of the technical plans for the week, so instead
I have been tying off loose ends and fixing bugs. The biggest milestone was
probably making it possible to browse remote IMAP servers using the Browse
tool, which paves the way for interactive configuration of import/index
policies when users don&#39;t want to rely on Mailpile&#39;s auto-detection (or need
to correct the auto-detector&#39;s mistakes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Plans for this week&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add missing configuration dialogues&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix easy buglets, hide features too hard to fix&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tag and startg packaging Beta III&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2015 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>License: The Python&#39;s Tongue</title>
    <link>http://www.mailpile.is/blog/2015-07-02_Licensing_Decision.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;It has been an interesting month!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally put the team&#39;s original plan into action, launching a vote
on our new &lt;a href=&#34;/roadmap/&#34;&gt;roadmap site&lt;/a&gt;, asking our community of backers
to help us choose a single license for the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were discussions on Twitter, &lt;a href=&#34;2015-06-15_Community_License_Feedback.html&#34;&gt;thoughtful blog posts and insightful
e-mails&lt;/a&gt;. And people voted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, while I was fast asleep my trusty robots disabled the voting
and made a snapshot of the voting database at midnight
California-time, July 1st. I got up the next morning and before making
breakfast I ran a quick &lt;em&gt;grep&lt;/em&gt; to get a hint of the results. I was not
happy with what I saw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not happy at all...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Raw, Cooked and Baked Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what I saw:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;51.39% in 258 votes for the GNU AGPL v3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;48.61% in 244 votes for the Apache License 2.0&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we have a winner! Sort of. Barely...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mulled it over for most of the day and recalculated that evening, this
time weighing each ballot by the USD amount donated by the voter,
excluding the project founders because putting a dollar amount on our
contributions is not trivial math. This balloting method led to Apache
winning by a surprisingly large margin. However, when I dug into the
results, it turns out the difference was down to a single four-figure
backer who voted for Apache.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reversing the results on the basis of one man&#39;s generosity would not
seem right at all... particularly when I had just excluded the
founding team (whose opinions I know quite well) and I know for a fact
that very vocal advocates of the winning license backed us by just as
much but neglected to cast their votes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I recalculated a third time, this time using the natural logarithm of
USD amounts. This rewards generosity while recognizing that wealth is
not evenly distributed. This time the AGPLv3 won again, albeit by an
even smaller margin than before: 50.81% vs 49.19%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I gave up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Python&#39;s Tongue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the surface of it, this is the worst possible outcome of our
license elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole point of the vote was to reach a consensus. Licensing tends to
be very divisive in the Free and Open Source Software community and the
Mailpile Team hoped that by using a transparent, open and fair process
we could reach a conclusion everyone could abide by.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although these results clearly don&#39;t really meet that bar, all we can do
is look for a silver lining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact is, voter participation in this election was quite low. 3041
people in total were eligible for voting, but we only had about 16.5% turnout.
Considering the subject matter (licensing, how dull!), it seems quite
reasonable to assume this means most of our backers just don&#39;t care, one
way or another. Even Stallman himself &lt;a href=&#34;2015-06-15_Community_License_Feedback.html&#34;&gt;commented&lt;/a&gt;
that both licenses were acceptable, although he of course prefers the
AGPL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that interpretation, the results look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8.5% in 258 votes for the GNU AGPL v3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8.0% in 244 votes for the Apache License 2.0&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;83.5% don&#39;t care enough to vote or were unaware of the elections&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So our community is indeed divided. But it&#39;s not divided right down the
middle, it&#39;s divided like a python&#39;s tongue. Mostly united in just
wanting Mailpile to exist, with an small split at the tip regarding the
license.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s not too bad!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Choosing a License&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what&#39;s next?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could extend the deadline, hope more people vote and a stronger
consensus emerges... but I don&#39;t really think that will work. The ratios
haven&#39;t really changed much since the first few days of the campaign.
I know, I&#39;ve been peeking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we really can&#39;t live with two licenses forever, a choice has to be
made. I am writing the bulk of the code these days and have no-one but
the community to answer to, so ultimately the decision sits with me.
Without a clear mandate from the election, I am going to have to take
responsibility and make the choice myself. People who don&#39;t like it will
know exactly who to blame...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s a scary thought, but what the heck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I choose the GNU Affero General Public License. Version 3.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That will be the license I apply to all future code I commit to the
Mailpile project and that is the license future contributors to the main
repo will have to agree to as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sorry Apache backers, I really hope we can still be friends! If you&#39;re
really bummed you do have the right to fork yesterday&#39;s code and carry
on without me. But I would much rather we worked together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;But... why?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I choose the AGPLv3, because I think it is the right license for this
project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not because it won the elections by a tiny margin, although that was of
course a factor. Not because my co-conspirators, Smári and Brennan, both
prefer it, although that also matters. I choose the AGPLv3 because I
think it fits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mailpile is a project about freedom. It is not a popularity contest or a
startup, it&#39;s not &#34;industry infrastructure&#34;, nor does it aim to be.
Mailpile is a political project which aims to improve the privacy and
digital independence of individuals everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Apache License is a wonderful thing, an open, generous, pragmatic,
apolitical license. The AGPLv3 on the other hand, is a political and
ethical line in the sand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so is Mailpile.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2015 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Fast Startup and Key Discovery</title>
    <link>http://www.mailpile.is/blog/2015-06-29_Fast_Startup_and_Key_Disco.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week was a very successful one here in Mailpile-code-land.
A whole bunch of loose ends got tied off, so this week Mailpile
is actually leaps and bounds more powerful than it was just a few
days ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been a bit behind schedule working towards Beta III, but
this week has been so good that I am now mostly caught up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The highlights are described below. Just please, don&#39;t expect me
to always be this productive!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Memory Hole&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussions about &#34;Memory Hole&#34; picked up some steam this week.
Memory Hole is the proposal to extend PGP/MIME to sign and possibly
encrypt some e-mail message headers, the Subject being the most
obvious candidate. This is a collaborative effort between multiple
e-mail security tools, and this week test messages were exchanged
with the developers of Enigmail, R2Mail2, Lavaboom and gpg4o.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although Memory Hole does not address all of &lt;a href=&#34;2014-11-21_To_PGP_MIME_Or_Not.html&#34;&gt;the issues I have with
PGP/MIME&lt;/a&gt;, it is a massive step in
the right direction. The fact that it is already getting support from
so many projects is very encouraging!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Key Discovery and Crypto Policies&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week I completed the &#34;Key Discovery&#34; milestone from &lt;a href=&#34;/roadmap/&#34;&gt;the 1.0
roadmap&lt;/a&gt;! It is now possible to search for PGP keys,
import and use while composing a message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This completes the work started by Brennan last October, which he
was unable to finish because the back-end (my domain) didn&#39;t
provide him with the data and APIs that he needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the process of wrapping that up I also finished implementing
smart &#34;crypto policies&#34;, whereby the app will suggest signing or
encrypting of outgoing mail depending on what we have received
from the recipients in the past. This is a critical part of
Mailpile&#39;s overall strategy to gradually ramp up the security of
e-mail without getting in people&#39;s way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once more user interface work has been done it will also be
possible to configure custom policies for individual contacts. So
you will be able to tell Mailpile that Alice always wants to
receive encrypted mail, but Bob hates digital signatures...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Fast Startup Progress&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fast Startup milestone for 1.0 (and Beta III) involves
completely revamping how Mailpile stores metadata and the search
index.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a big and scary task, but luckily most of the research
and code was done last January. I spent a few days this week
dusting off the code and finished integrating it. The good news
is that it works: this weekend I started up a fully functioning
Mailpile using the new storage systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have yet to migrate the contacts over and write a migration
tool to help existing users make the switch, but the riskiest
parts of the job are now done. Because this is not a backwards
compatible change, this code won&#39;t be merged with the main branch
until the migration tool is written but will instead live on a
branch of its own:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/tree/features/metadata.ng&#34;&gt;features/metadata.ng&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Working with Mailing Lists&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another small improvement made this week involves how Mailpile
handles mailing lists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response to some feedback (a.k.a. friendly complaints) on our
IRC channel (#mailpile), I&#39;ve made the search keyword generation
for mailing lists both less spammy and more precise. The metadata
store now also records which mailing list a message came from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I&#39;m a bit more used to working with Mailpile&#39;s user
interface, I was also able to make these improvements bubble all
the way up so people can make use of them! If you select a single
message in the search view, Mailpile&#39;s tool bar will now display
a link to search for other messages from the same person - or
from the same mailing list, based on these improved keywords.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an attempt to educate users on the possibility and syntax
of searching by sender or by mailing list.  But it is also
directly functional, because once you are looking at a search
result page dedicated to a particular mailing list, the &#34;Save
Search&#34; button makes it trivially easy to convert that into a
dedicated Tag with a behind-the-scenes Filter classifying future
e-mail automatically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Powerful features, made discoverable and clickable...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Plans for this week&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tally votes and announce our license!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finish Fast Startup for contacts and migration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find someone to review the crypto used by new storage systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Begin work on Beta III packaging&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2015 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>The DCSS Conference in Cardiff</title>
    <link>http://www.mailpile.is/blog/2015-06-22_DCSS_Cardiff.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This weekly report covers two weeks of work, because last week&#39;s post was
dedicated to community feedback on the licensing debate. Here are some of
the tech issues that got resolved in the meantime:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IMAP: Improved download speed and Dovecot compatibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Security: Fixed serious bug in local data encryption&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Security: Implemented basic PGP passphrase manager&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fast setup: Editing accounts now works&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fast setup: Usability tests at DCSS, found and fixed some issues&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UI: Tag creation and editing were revamped&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Composer: Fixed bugs, started refactor to handle key discovery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Packaging: Prepared the packaging robot for Beta III builds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week I took some much needed days off and then attended the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dcssproject.net/&#34;&gt;Digital
Citizenship and Surveillance Society&lt;/a&gt;
conference in Cardiff.  It was a very inspiring conference and the
organizers&#39; goal of getting techies to rub shoulders with academics and
usability people was, as far as Mailpile goes, a complete success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first day was mainly dedicated to presentations and interesting
conversations, including a well received lightning talk about Mailpile
itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the second day I performed two small usability tests with non-technical
volunteers from the conference and discussed overall UI strategy with some
of the experts from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.headlondon.com/&#34;&gt;Head London&lt;/a&gt;. Actionable
results were filed as &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/issues&#34;&gt;issues in our bug
tracker&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On both days I did a fair bit of brainstorming with developers from the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://leap.se/&#34;&gt;Leap&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://pixelated-project.org/&#34;&gt;Pixelated&lt;/a&gt;
projects, in particular helping them get up to speed with the e-mail header
protection work that was done at &lt;a href=&#34;2015-04-20_OpenPGP_Email_Summit.html&#34;&gt;April&#39;s GnuPG e-mail
summit&lt;/a&gt;. I summarized those
discussions in &lt;a href=&#34;https://lists.gnupg.org/pipermail/gnupg-devel/2015-June/030036.html&#34;&gt;a post to the GnuPG-devel mailing
list&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, it was an excellent conference. I had fun and came home
feeling inspired and motivated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just what the doctor ordered!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Plans for this week&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finish refactoring the composer and key discovery code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Migrate metadata index to new storage format&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2015 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Licensing: Your Feedback So Far</title>
    <link>http://www.mailpile.is/blog/2015-06-15_Community_License_Feedback.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;[ &lt;em&gt;Note: I&#39;m taking most of the week off to recharge my batteries and attend
the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dcssproject.net/conference/&#34;&gt;Digital Citizenship and Surveillance Society conference and
hackathon&lt;/a&gt;
- the next weekly update will happen next Monday.&lt;/em&gt; ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are now &lt;strong&gt;2 weeks left&lt;/strong&gt; until we close &lt;a href=&#34;/roadmap/&#34;&gt;the polls&lt;/a&gt; and
choose a license for Mailpile 1.0. Some members of our community have
written blog posts about what they would prefer, others have tweeted,
and still others have sent us e-mail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We may not agree with all of the points made, but it&#39;s a complex issue and
your feedback matters. Thank you all!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is dedicated to preserving and publicizing your thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Blog Posts&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Geir Freysson writes: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.geirfreysson.com/2015/06/why-the-crypto-email-client-mailpile-should-use-the-apache-software-license/&#34;&gt;Mailpile should use the Apache software
license&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea behind the Apache license is to, quoting Chairman Mao, “let a thousand flowers bloom” and allow as many people and companies as possible to build on the software regardless of whether the incentive is commercial or altruistic.
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.geirfreysson.com/2015/06/why-the-crypto-email-client-mailpile-should-use-the-apache-software-license/&#34;&gt;read more&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Franklin M. Siler writes: &lt;a href=&#34;http://franksiler.com/on-choosing-open-licenses/&#34;&gt;On choosing open licenses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The essential idea here is that I want my projects to contribute back, but I want to do so voluntarily. I particularly want to avoid a situation where I need to implement “special sauce” in a component, but then may have to release that code out into the marketplace- there’s no particularly good reason I would want to take on, say, a virally licensed webserver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of choosing feedstock, it’s often hit or miss, but I always look at the licenses before I start, particularly for “scaffolding code” that will wind up being the core of an app.
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://franksiler.com/on-choosing-open-licenses/&#34;&gt;read more&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;E-mail&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From: Richard Stallman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read your posting about the question of which license to use on your
source code henceforth. I urge you to use the GNU Affero GPL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason is simple: so that companies that improve Mailpile and put
their versions into public use will make their improvements available to
the Mailpile community.  The AGPL would achieve this.  The Apache
license, which is a weak, permissive license, would not try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of these licenses qualify as free/libre; neither of them is
unethical.  Given a choice between two ethically valid options, you
should choose the one that is better in practice, and that is the GNU
AGPL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;http://gnu.org/licenses/license-recommendations.html&#34;&gt;http://gnu.org/licenses/license-recommendations.html&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&#34;http://gnu.org/licenses/license-list.html&#34;&gt;http://gnu.org/licenses/license-list.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-- &lt;br /&gt;
Dr Richard Stallman&lt;br /&gt;
President, Free Software Foundation (gnu.org, fsf.org)&lt;br /&gt;
Internet Hall-of-Famer (&amp;lt;internethalloffame.org)&lt;br /&gt;
Skype: No way! See stallman.org/skype.html.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; From: Maxim Cournoyer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear mailpile team,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As stated on the mailpile homepage:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mailpile is an effort to reclaim private communication on the
Internet. A project to rescue our personal lives from the proprietary
cloud and prevent our conversations from being strip-mined for corporate
profit and government surveillance. Mailpile is taking e-mail back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is my opinion that the license that would better support these goals
would be the GNU Affero GPLv3 license as it protects the freedom for
anyone to audit the source of the software, no matter where and how it
is deployed. From a security perspective this is a must.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for hearing my voice,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maxim Cournoyer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From: Phil Hughes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, about your tweet about being accused of bias. Yeah, when people
bitch about your bias but in different directions, I do think it means
you are in the middle. Being a Linux guy for 20+ years and ex-publisher
of Linux Journal, this situation has happened to me many, many times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My intent was to comment on &#34;which is the better license&#34; but, after
reading your blog I really don&#39;t have &#34;the right answer&#34;. Hopefully
others will offer more thoughts so that the decision will become
obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My &#34;bias&#34; is that the GPL irritates me -- mostly because of RMS&#39;s &#34;this
is the only answer&#34; attitude. I am 100% behind the goal of the GPL (and
I think he knows that) but I also recognize the down-sides. For example,
at one point Linus was asked what was his biggest error with Linux and
he said &#34;licensing it under the GPL&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His comment was about the &#34;politics&#34; of the GPL rather than the concept.
That&#39;s pretty much my issue as well. It is hard to get those &#34;afraid&#34; of
the GPL on board when you are put in a position where you need to defend
RMS&#39;s politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know that Apple picked a &#34;we can do what we want&#34; license for its
base software. If BSD and Linux has both been under the same license,
things probably would have been different. But, better? It is hard to
say.  Those who are actually there to innovate seem OK with the GPL. GPL
or not, it is still hard to measure which license actually produces more
innovation. I expect there are big wins for each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, now you see my bias and you also see that it didn&#39;t produce a
decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully others will chip in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-- &lt;br /&gt;
Phil Hughes&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From: Tim Herklots&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &#34;Network Use is Distribution&#34; feature of AGPL plus the
no-sublicensing makes it much easier to detect license abuse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the code is detected somewhere in the wild, and source isn&#39;t
available, AGPL is always violated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The threat model that concerns me is someone big like Microsoft, Google,
Facebook, Yahoo forking the cord and including an government-breakable
alternative encryption type/method that their installs use by default or
by rollback at the mailserver end. Mailpile would be forced to include
this alternative for compatibility reasons, and the bad encryption
becomes standardised with most people thinking that it is good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tim&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2015 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
</channel></rss>