<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
  <title>Mailpile: The Mailpile Blog</title>
  <link>https://www.mailpile.is/blog/</link>
  <item>
    <title>A Mail Client in Six Steps</title>
    <link>https://www.mailpile.is/blog/2023-05-01_A_Mail_Client_in_Six_Steps.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Good news, friends!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mailpile and the fine folks &lt;a href=&#34;https://nlnet.net/&#34;&gt;NLNet&lt;/a&gt; are in the process of exchanging signed copies of a Memorandum of Understanding!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&#39;s an MoU? So glad you asked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What this means, is that NLNet are going to support the next few months of Mailpile work with a grant,
as part of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://nlnet.nl/entrust/&#34;&gt;NGI Zero Entrust&lt;/a&gt; initiative.
The tag-line for NGI Zero Entrust is &#34;Trustworthiness and data sovereignty&#34;,
and I&#39;m pretty chuffed that NLNet agree Mailpile is on topic for that theme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Memorandum of Understanding is the final stage of our acceptance into this program;
it is a description of what work they are supporting with the grant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The work we are about to undertake is summarized
&lt;a href=&#34;https://nlnet.nl/project/Mailpile2-Moggie/&#34;&gt;on their website&lt;/a&gt;
like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mailpile&#39;s mission is to empower users to be more autonomous and private in how they manage, store and communicate over e-mail,
simplifying the use of relevant encryption technology (OpenPGP, Tor and encrypted local storage).
Mailpile 2 will be an Open Source, secure web-mail application,
usable and powerful enough to be a compelling alternative to both mainstream desktop e-mail clients and proprietary web-mail services.
Mailpile 2 will offer both local and remote access to an elegant,
mobile-friendly web interface, built on web-APIs exposed by Moggie.
Moggie is the project&#39;s technical toolkit for searching and working with e-mail.
This stage of the project is about developing Moggie to the point where it is useful as a stand-alone tool in its own right,
and feature complete enough that work on the Mailpile 2 user-interface can commence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Plan: ship moggie!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The MoU lays out further details.
It defines six milestones which take us from where we are now,
to a working terminal-mode (text based) e-mail client called moggie.
Moggie&#39;s back-end will have a documented API,
which can be used to build other e-mail clients or mail processing tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The milestones:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deliver a read-only e-mail client&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add search-engine (search/filter/tag) functionality to the e-mail client&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add writing capabilities to the e-mail client&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add the ability to compose and send e-mail to the client&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add user interfaces and documentation for configuration to the client&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complete a security review cycle and make a public release&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security, autonomy and encryption (including OpenPGP) are part of every stage of this plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of these steps should take roughly one month,
and after each milestone code will be published on GitHub and there will be a blog post discussing how things went.
So stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that in six months (give or take...),
we aim to ship a powerful new tool, &lt;em&gt;moggie&lt;/em&gt;,
which provide a terminal-based e-mail client and toolkit for shell scripting and automating various e-mail related tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But moggie is also designed to be the back-end for a much more user-friendly web-based e-mail client: &lt;strong&gt;Mailpile version 2&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Backstory&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This plan is, on its surface, a bit crazy.
Going from zero to mail client in six months
(with grand security ambitions and only one developer, myself)
would be a very tall order!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily we aren&#39;t starting from zero.
This plan builts on almost two years of behind-the-scenes development.
We already have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a working search engine,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a filtering system,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a configuration system,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;support for multiple mailbox formats,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;encrypted local storage, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a powerful system for processing HTML-only e-mail,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://passcrow.org/&#34;&gt;a secure password recovery scheme&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;partial OpenPGP support,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a partial prototype for a text-mode mail client&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;... built on a web-API back-end&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;... which is exposed as a set of unix-style command-line tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a complete rewrite of Mailpile, from the ground up.
It is faster and more efficient,
it uses less RAM,
and it makes better use of modern multi-core CPUs.
And of course moggie is written in Python 3
- no more obsolete Python 2 dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of inspiration
(and code fragments whenever possible)
were of course taken from the old app.
But moggie really is a new thing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s time to polish it off,
tie up the loose ends and share the results with the wider community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is exacty what NLNet are going to help us do. :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please join the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://community.mailpile.is/t/a-grant-from-nlnet-a-mail-client-in-six-steps/1054&#34;&gt;discussion about this post&lt;/a&gt;
on our community forum.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Rebooting Mailpile</title>
    <link>https://www.mailpile.is/blog/2022-11-30_Rebooting_Mailpile.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Long time no blog!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been a few updates on the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://community.mailpile.is/&#34;&gt;the Community Forum&lt;/a&gt;,
but nothing here for quite a while!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a short post to update everyone on the current status of the project:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Mailpile v1 codebase is no longer being updated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mailpile v2 is making progress, in semi-stealth mode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In parallel, a project to create a dedicated hardware device for Mailpile is underway&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main reason for these changes,
is that Python 2 is no longer maintained or supported by the community,
and I decided that rewriting the whole thing in Python 3 made more sense than attempting to port the old code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The old code remains a useful resource,
both for inspiration and sometimes for copying code directly over,
but enough things are new that it&#39;s most accurate to call Mailpile v2 a new application.
The code-name for the v2 project is &lt;em&gt;moggie&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s going well,
but I haven&#39;t made any public releases yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch this space for further updates.
Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2022 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>CCCamp19 and further EFail mitigations</title>
    <link>https://www.mailpile.is/blog/2019-08-31_CCCamp_EFail.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello world!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I write this, I have mostly recovered from the amazing Chaos
Communication Camp in Germany. I attended the camp mostly as a holiday,
but there were of course quite a few Mailpile related discussions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most interesting of those related to EFail. I spent a couple of
afternoons sitting in the shade with researchers and developers who
work on OpenPGP related things. We discussed &lt;a href=&#34;https://efail.de/&#34;&gt;EFail&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those of you who haven&#39;t heard of EFail, it was one of the most
serious vulnerabilities the OpenPGP community has ever had to deal with:
by combining flaws in e-mail clients with flaws in legacy PGP (and
S/MIME) implementations, EFail described multiple ways an attacker could
turn a vulnerable e-mail client into a decryption oracle and steal the
cleartext of previously secured communications. Cryptosystem flaws don&#39;t
get much worse than that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was such a serious issue that the EFF recommended people disable
PGP entirely, at least for a little while. This triggered a rather
emotional backlash from the PGP community, and unfortunately a lot of
misinformation and misunderstandings were published. Some of which
still have not been corrected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a community, we&#39;re still coming to terms with some of the
implications. Those of us who aren&#39;t in denial (which is disturbingly
common) are still mulling over ways to secure our tools and defend
against similar flaws in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have written before about &lt;a href=&#34;2018-05-14_PGP_Security_Alert.html&#34;&gt;Mailpile and
EFail&lt;/a&gt;: there were a few issues that
needed fixing, but overall Mailpile weathered EFail relatively well.
Exfiltrating cleartext from Mailpile was possible, but it was not fully
automated and required social engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The social engineering aspects are still quite serious, and some are
easier to exploit than others. The most trivial EFail exploit is to
send someone a message they&#39;re likely to reply to, with the ciphertext
you want to exfiltrate appended to the end after a long boring
boilerplate signature or quoted message. If the mail client decrypts,
and the recipient replies without reading and pruning their response...
hey presto, you&#39;ve exfiltratrated the secret message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the outcomes of these discussions at camp, were some concrete
recommendations on how Mailpile could make such social engineering less
likely to succeed. The guiding principle I ended up with, was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the user is probably not going to see the content, do not decrypt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the plane home from Germany, I implemented this strategy. So for the
first time, Mailpile will deliberately decline to decrypt parts of
incoming e-mail, if the message structure is such that it might might
provide cover for EFail social engineering attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The change wasn&#39;t huge, but the security impact is significant. We
welcome any and all feedback: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/commit/79551b17928a9f990ac5e1336386caab8b183323&#34;&gt;the code is here&lt;/a&gt;.
This patch is already in &lt;a href=&#34;/download/linux.html&#34;&gt;the nightly packages&lt;/a&gt;
and will hit the release branch next time I update it - which should be
soon, we&#39;ve got quite a few important fixes queued up by now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://sebastian-schinzel.de/&#34;&gt;Sebastian&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/valodim&#34;&gt;Vincent&lt;/a&gt; for helping me figure out how to
improve Mailpile on this front. And thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ccc.de/&#34;&gt;CCC&lt;/a&gt;
for providing venues for these conversations to take place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please feel free to &lt;a href=&#34;https://community.mailpile.is/t/blog-post-about-cccamp-19-and-efail/243&#34;&gt;discuss this post in our Community
Forum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2019 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Burned Out and Happy?</title>
    <link>https://www.mailpile.is/blog/2019-04-06_Burnout.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Mailpile Users and Backers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just wanted to post a short note, to explain why development has been
so slow for the last year - or longer. The long and the short of it is,
I&#39;m burned out, and this has been the case for quite some time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I care deeply about this project, but it really is too big for one
person and I haven&#39;t successfully built a team to support me. That&#39;s not
to discount the contributions and efforts of our community, but at the
end of the day I&#39;ve been the one responsible for keeping the ball
rolling. I review the pull requests, I respond to issues, I file the tax
returns, I try to spend your donations wisely... and I write most of the
code. Doing this well is a lot of work!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This responsibility, combined with frustration over how slow progress
has been, has really worn me down. When I&#39;m feeling down, I&#39;m not very
productive, leading to a vicious cycle of feeling bad about a the lack
of progress and then becoming incapable of making progress as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s not good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took me a while to realize what was going on, to realize I was burned
out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also a money dimension here; although I cannot say thank you
enough for all the donations and support from our community, the fact is
that Mailpile has not been able to pay me a decent wage for my work,
&lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt;. I know my value on the job market, and I&#39;ve been underpaid since
day one. That was my choice and I don&#39;t regret it; but it&#39;s still become
harder and harder for me to justify. I have a family now and I&#39;ve
drained most of my savings trying to get 1.0 out the door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I&#39;m giving myself a break and focusing on other things for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve gotten a (part-time) job working with the fine folks at
&lt;a href=&#34;https://isnic.is/&#34;&gt;ISNIC&lt;/a&gt;, I&#39;m working out regularly at the pool and
I&#39;m spending more time with friends and family. &lt;em&gt;Life is good!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I&#39;ve accepted and embraced my burnout, I&#39;m actually feeling
pretty happy.  Identifying a problem is the first step towards a
resolution, and I&#39;m already well on my way with steps two and three.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to be 100% clear: &lt;strong&gt;Mailpile is not dead!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Far from it, I&#39;m way too proud of this app to just walk away and let it
die. But for now, Mailpile has been demoted to a part time job at most,
and a beloved hobby at worst. Considering how unproductive I had become,
you may not even notice any difference...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, if reading this gives you the urge to help out, here are a few
things you can do for me and for Mailpile:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/download/&#34;&gt;Use Mailpile&lt;/a&gt;! It&#39;s not perfect, but it&#39;s pretty great.
&lt;li&gt;Tweet or &lt;a href=&#34;https://joinmastodon.org/&#34;&gt;toot&lt;/a&gt; what you like about it...
    I&#39;m listening!
&lt;li&gt;Help make our &lt;a href=&#34;https://community.mailpile.is/categories&#34;&gt;Community Discourse&lt;/a&gt;
    a useful, welcoming place.
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/donate/&#34;&gt;Donate&lt;/a&gt;: As always, I&#39;ll do my best to spend it wisely.
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-- Bjarni&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2019 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Community Discourse: Launched!</title>
    <link>https://www.mailpile.is/blog/2019-02-15_Community_Discourse.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello Mailpile world!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have launched a new site for community discussions about Mailpile:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://community.mailpile.is/categories&#34;&gt;community.mailpile.is&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The site runs the excellent &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.discourse.org/&#34;&gt;Discourse&lt;/a&gt; software,
which means it&#39;s primarily an accessible web-based discussion forum, but it can
also be used as a mailing list for those who prefer such things. Our Discourse
was set up by a kind member of our community, &lt;b&gt;Greg Sutcliffe&lt;/b&gt;. Thanks
Greg! And thanks &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/asta_fish&#34;&gt;Ásta&lt;/a&gt; for helping me launch
the site properly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the site is to give people a searchable, &#34;on the record&#34; venue to
&lt;a href=&#34;https://community.mailpile.is/c/uncategorized&#34;&gt;discuss Mailpile, provide feedback, exchange tips and
tricks&lt;/a&gt; - and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://community.mailpile.is/c/support&#34;&gt;get support&lt;/a&gt;. The forum is brand new and
pretty empty at the moment, so please feel free to post something and start a
conversation!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more ephemeral discussions, we still have
&lt;a href=&#34;https://webchat.freenode.net/?channels=%23mailpile&amp;amp;uio=d4&#34;&gt;#mailpile on Freenode&lt;/a&gt;,
and for bug reports we have
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/issues&#34;&gt;GitHub Issues&lt;/a&gt;. The Community site
is for everything else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Including &lt;a href=&#34;https://community.mailpile.is/t/community-discourse-launched/31&#34;&gt;discussions about our blog
posts!&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
</channel></rss>