<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
  <title>Mailpile: The Mailpile Blog</title>
  <link>http://www.mailpile.is/blog/</link>
  <item>
    <title>Thank you!</title>
    <link>http://www.mailpile.is/blog/2015-08-24_Thank_You.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;After posting last week about fatigue and burnout, a lot of people
reached out and offered encouragement or support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really appreciate it: thank you all!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the code front things have been mostly quiet since last week,
because I have been trying to get some rest. I&#39;m not very good at
that, to be honest, but I try. In spite of myself, I made some
progress on speeding up the web UI (in my private branch) and some
friendly volunteers from our community of translators have both found
and fixed a bunch of typos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grant work progresses, slowly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tasks for this week&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tasks for this week are the same as last week:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not burn out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Really finish the OTF grant proposal for real&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write some code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 24 Aug 2015 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>On Crowdfunding and Burnout</title>
    <link>http://www.mailpile.is/blog/2015-08-18_On_Crowdfunding_and_Burnout.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Being on fire isn&#39;t always awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On fire and burnout are two sides of the same coin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And to be completely honest with you, dear backers, I&#39;m on the verge of
burnout over here. I have been pushing myself too hard this summer,
trying to make 1.0 happen. I&#39;m cranky on the IRC channel, prickly with
my friends. The smallest set-backs trigger overreactions: rage, sadness,
or the worst - apathy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been here before; it means I&#39;ve been working too hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been on fire this summer, in the good sense. An amazing amount of
progress has been made. But lately this whole thing has felt more like
trying to burn a wet newspaper. No flames, just a soggy mess. I light
the match and nothing happens. If I keep at it, I&#39;ll just burn myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I need to take it easy for a bit. My July vacation in Iceland ended
up being mostly work and I&#39;m paying the price for that now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Dark Side of Crowdfunding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crowd-funding has a dark side to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As wonderful as it may be to have a large group of people rooting for
you, the more people backed a project, the more people will be let down
if you fail to ship. The more people trusted your vision enough to give
you money, the greater the pressure not to betray their trust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many startup founders buckle under the pressure of keeping a business
afloat and meeting the expectations of their investors. &lt;a href=&#34;http://startupdepression.com/&#34;&gt;Startup
depression&lt;/a&gt; is a thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crowd-funding adds another dimension to that; investors understand risks
and they accept they may lose their money. But when the general public
backs a project, that isn&#39;t necessarily the case. They&#39;re not pros.
They&#39;re a bunch of &lt;em&gt;really nice people who decided to support your
vision&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You really don&#39;t want to let them down!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mailpile may not be a startup in the normal sense of the word, but we do
share many of the same issues. We - you, me, all the project&#39;s backers -
are creating something new, something ambitious. Running out of money is
always a concern; everyone has to eat. We may not expect to make
millions of dollars, but we do hope to have millions of users. We&#39;re not
out to &#34;disrupt e-mail&#34; for financial gain, but we do want to have an
impact. Our reputations are at stake. And although we may not have taken
money from investors, we did take money from our community of backers
and supporters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when I read about startup founders struggling to cope, I know exactly
what they&#39;re talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not quite sure what do do about it though. Except try and take it
easy and try to keep making progress. One without the other doesn&#39;t
seem to work, deadlines be damned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Weekly Report&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This last week has been slow, for all of the above reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made some progress on the OTF grant proposal, but it&#39;s a tricky beast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally implemented the auto-configuration tool that will try very
hard to guess all your settings when you add a new account. It&#39;s
actually pretty awesome, so that&#39;s something!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got the Transifex source strings updated, so Mailpile 1.0 will exist
in more languages than just English.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, I decided to take steps to avoid burning out. Writing
this has been cathartic. I&#39;m going to get some rest. And I&#39;m going to
try and get more face-time with friendly people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pyconuk.org/&#34;&gt;see you at PyCon&lt;/a&gt;! :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tasks for this week&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not burn out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work on the OTF grant proposal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write some code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 18 Aug 2015 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Github Issue Cleanup Frenzy</title>
    <link>http://www.mailpile.is/blog/2015-08-10_Issue_Cleanup_Frenzy.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The last week was mostly dedicated to administration work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important task was communicating with our new accountants. The
firm that did our taxes last year actually went out of business a couple
of months ago... never a good sign!  So one of my top-priority tasks
while I was in Iceland was to finda a new accountant. I succeeded, went
with a medium-sized company that actually has a web-site but has been in
business since 1995 and they seem quite solid; last week I spent some
time communicating with them so they could get to work filing the
project&#39;s annual return.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there was another money related task: Mailpile has a grant
application in the pipes with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.opentechfund.org/&#34;&gt;OTF&lt;/a&gt;
for quite some time now. Due to personal work overload, I have been
putting off responding to questions they had for far too long.  Last
week I finally restarted the conversation and started revising the
application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third administration task was the most time consuming: I set out to
clean up and curate our &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/issues&#34;&gt;giant pile of Github
issues&lt;/a&gt;. I am ashamed to
say that many bug reports and support requests never got answered,
because there were simply too many for us to keep up. So I spent a fair
bit of time last week reading issue after issue after issue, typing
responses and sorting, or simply writing code when the fix was obvious
and straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also will be an on-going task; I don&#39;t actually expect to ever
close all the issues, as many are discussions or ideas for plug-ins or
spin-off projects. But before our 1.0 I&#39;d like to have responded to
every single bug-report, filed it appropriately and removed any that are
duplicates or obsolete. You can see my frenzy in action on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/pulse/monthly&#34;&gt;project
pulse dashboard&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I recently discovered that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.transifex.com/projects/p/mailpile/&#34;&gt;our Transifex account&lt;/a&gt;
has not updated the translation source strings for &lt;em&gt;months&lt;/em&gt;. This is
not yet fixed, but will be soon...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s a lot of admin work!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the code front, I fixed a bunch of minor bugs, merged them into the
beta branch and updated our &lt;a href=&#34;/download/&#34;&gt;downloadable packages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also made a lot of progress on speeding up the apps web user
interface. Hopefully I&#39;ll be able to include the fruits of that work in
another update to the beta branch next week. Fingers crossed!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tasks for this week&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finish updating the OTF grant proposal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep cleaning up the Github issue tracker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get the Transifex source strings updated!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Autoajax: speed up the web UI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2015 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Vacation over; Back to work!</title>
    <link>http://www.mailpile.is/blog/2015-08-03_Back_to_Work.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Time for the weekly update!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Updates have been a bit less frequent of late, as I have spent a fair
bit of the last month on holidays; spending time with family in Iceland
and catching up with friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Mailpile work got done as well:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Beta III was release&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A brainstorming and hack session with CloudFleet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work began on accelerating the Mailpile web UI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also began exploring more seriously the possibility of shipping a
webkit-based container along with the desktop version of Mailpile. This
would go a long way towards fixing the largest outstanding usability
concerns of Beta III. We&#39;ll see how that goes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Plans for this week&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More Mailpile UI work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Update Beta III with minor bugfixes and improvements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See you next week!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2015 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Mailpile Beta III: WYSIWYG</title>
    <link>http://www.mailpile.is/blog/2015-07-20_Mailpile_Beta_III.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello world!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are proud to announce the our third Beta release:
&lt;strong&gt;Mailpile Beta III&lt;/strong&gt; (v0.5.1)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This release&#39;s code name is &#34;What You See Is What You Get - WYSIWYG&#34;.
The main focus of this release is simplicity and stability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where Can You Get It?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new release is availble from &lt;a href=&#34;/download/&#34;&gt;the Mailpile download
page&lt;/a&gt;, and the source is &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/releases&#34;&gt;on
github&lt;/a&gt; as always.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please read &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/wiki/Release-Notes-201507-Beta-III&#34;&gt;the release
notes&lt;/a&gt;
and check our &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/wiki/Security-roadmap&#34;&gt;security
roadmap&lt;/a&gt; so
you know what to expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What&#39;s New?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Setup is simpler and multiple account support is much improved.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initial setup was slimmed down to a mere two steps: choose your language
and choose your password. We are a bit sad that this rendered obsolete
the quirky silly hints we provided while folks waited for their e-mail
to start downloading, but maybe we&#39;ll be able to make use of that
elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recognition of our users&#39; need to manage multiple e-mail accounts
and play different roles, accounts are now a core feature and the app
sports a new &#34;Home Page&#34; which highlights which accounts you have
configured and provides shortcuts for reading or composing mail within
the scope of each one. When configuring a new account we now make use of
the Mozilla ISPDB (Internet Service Provider Database) to avoid the need
to manually enter settings for most larger e-mail providers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, for the geeks in the room that already have piles of e-mail on
their local machines, we&#39;ve added the &lt;strong&gt;Browse&lt;/strong&gt; tool which lets you
find local mailboxes and interactively add them to your pile. Unix mbox,
Maildir and Mac Mail formats are currently supported out of the box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key discovery works.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Searching for encryption keys, both in local mail and on remote key
servers should now work reasonably well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you see is what you get!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the unfinished and half-baked user-interface elements have been
removed. The dedicated Tags and Contacts pages are gone for now, as are
many buttons and links which seemed like good ideas but never quite
worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are still some loose ends, but for the most part the Mailpile user
interface now keeps its implicit promises: what you see is what you get!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What&#39;s still broken?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The app is still very slow to start up if you have a large amount of
e-mail or many contacts, and still relies on the external &lt;code&gt;openssl&lt;/code&gt;
process which has proven buggy in some critical cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The web interface is slow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remote access to a running Mailpile still requires advanced tech skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The app&#39;s communiction with the outside world needs to be better
secured; SSL certificates need to be varified and our Tor integration
for anonymizing keyserver lookups is unfinished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting the app is still a confusing experience for most Windows and
Mac users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When preparing the Beta, we discovered that our translation teams on
Transifex hadn&#39;t received updated strings to work with in quite some
time, so most translations are woefully out of date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What&#39;s next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fixing all of the above!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week I am going to update our &lt;a href=&#34;2015-04-27_Roadmap_to_v1.html&#34;&gt;Roadmap to Version
1.0&lt;/a&gt; and spend some time working with the
fine fellows from &lt;a href=&#34;https://cloudfleet.io/&#34;&gt;Cloudfleet&lt;/a&gt; who are coming to
visit Iceland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing however has been decided: until the 1.0 is released, the Beta
III packages will be updated roughly once every two weeks. So watch
those version numbers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks and happy mailing!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2015 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
</channel></rss>