<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
  <title>Mailpile: The Mailpile Blog</title>
  <link>http://www.mailpile.is/blog/</link>
  <item>
    <title>Roadmap Reality Check</title>
    <link>http://www.mailpile.is/blog/2015-06-01_Roadmap_Reality_Check.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;First, an announcment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Invitations to the voting page have been sent!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All 3015 of them!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you donated $23 USD (or more) to the project and haven&#39;t yet received
an invitation, please &lt;strong&gt;check your spam&lt;/strong&gt;. If nothing&#39;s there, please
&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:team@mailpile.is?subject=Community+Site&#34;&gt;get in touch&lt;/a&gt;. We might
not have a valid e-mail address for you on file, or it may be that
things just got lost in the shuffle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voting on the license will continue &lt;strong&gt;until July 1&lt;/strong&gt;, at which point I will
call the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hooray!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Roadmap Distractions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to getting the invitations sent out this last week has been
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/commits/master&#34;&gt;very productive on a the code
front&lt;/a&gt;... just not
entirely on the stuff I was &lt;em&gt;supposed&lt;/em&gt; to be working on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Distractions included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Going over the settings of our Twitter and Facebook accounts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making the app less pretty (temporarily, to manage expectations)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding in-app instructions on how best to report bugs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Responding to some Github issues, fixed some buglets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implementing working proxy support (HTTP, SOCKS and Tor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implementing &#34;select all matching this search&#34;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last two in particular are both awesome milestones in their own
right, things which had been languishing at 90% in our code-base for
&lt;em&gt;months&lt;/em&gt; now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proxy support allows us to start testing some of the main points
from &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/wiki/Security-roadmap&#34;&gt;the security
roadmap&lt;/a&gt;,
with respect to anonymous access to SMTP, IMAP servers and Gravatar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being able to &#34;select all&#34; makes the app an order of magnitude more
powerful when it comes to organizing and extracting value from e-mail.
Basic operations like &#34;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/issues/1027&#34;&gt;mark all messages as
read&lt;/a&gt;&#34; depend on this,
as did more advanced use cases, such as using
&lt;a href=&#34;2015-05-18_Digging_for_Data.html&#34;&gt;Datadig&lt;/a&gt; to convert hundreds of
PayPal notifications into a spreadsheet of Mailpile backers...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why you no focus?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this is the third week in a row with some pretty major, exciting
distractions. Great progress, but not necessarily on things which were
due according to the roadmap. What&#39;s going on?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would hate to be my manager, but this is relatively normal; business
as usual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t know if this works the same way for other software developers,
but after 20 years of coding for fun and profit I have learned that I am
most productive if I have goals and deadlines, balanced with the freedom
to frequently give in to inspiration and obsession. The above work falls
squarely into the latter category; I got inspired and could visualize
exactly how to solve each problem. Rather than put it off, I harnessed
that creative energy and just &lt;em&gt;got things done&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s all necessary, useful work. It&#39;s just not happening in the order
laid out in the original plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that does beg the question: how is &lt;a href=&#34;2015-04-27_Roadmap_to_v1.html&#34;&gt;the roadmap
itself&lt;/a&gt; holding up?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Roadmap Reality Check&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the roadmap, the &#34;Short Setup Flow&#34; theme should be complete now.
It is not, I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; behind schedule. This is roughly where various
roadmap-related tasks stand at the moment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;90%&lt;/strong&gt; - Browse FS: Works! Is a bit ugly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;90%&lt;/strong&gt; - Accounts: The design is now pretty solid (in my head).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;80%&lt;/strong&gt; - Key discovery: results need to be injected back into the composer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;80%&lt;/strong&gt; - Browse Mailboxes: mail can be read without being added to the
             search index first, but is buggy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;75%&lt;/strong&gt; - Account creation: almost works! This replaces the crypto,
             profile, route and source setup pages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;60%&lt;/strong&gt; - Simplified UI: More cleanup is needed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;40%&lt;/strong&gt; - Home Page: is live, but unfinished.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10%&lt;/strong&gt; - Browsing IMAP/POP3: should be easy, but barely started.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, I figure I&#39;m about a week or two behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could be worse, releasing Beta III in about a month&#39;s time is still
feasible. A bit crazy, but feasible...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Plans for this week&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Admin work: Taxes and pay my own salary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finish the Add Account tool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upgrade the Add Account code so it also functions as Edit Account.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Either IMAP browsing work or start merging the new storage code
   required for faster startup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>An AMA with the Localization Lab</title>
    <link>http://www.mailpile.is/blog/2015-05-25_Localization_Lab_AMA.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week&#39;s big event was a very entertaining &#34;Ask Me Anything&#34;
session with the folks from the Open Technology Fund&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.localizationlab.org/&#34;&gt;Localization
Lab&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a friendly and productive session which hopefully helped
strengthen the ties between the coding side of the Mailpile project and
the very important community of volunteers that translate our software
to languages other than English. There were two main take-aways from the
meeting, aside from getting to know each other a bit better:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mailpile&#39;s core includes a plug-in designed to help translators,
   which can be enabled with &lt;code&gt;mailpile&amp;gt; plugins/load i18nhelper&lt;/code&gt;. It
   would be useful to develop this further and get feedback from the
   translators themselves on how it could be improved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The efforts of our translators are valuable and deserve to be
   publicly recognized, just like the efforts of our other backers.
   The Localization Lab folks were going to see what they could do
   to compile a list of contributors, and I was going to make sure
   that list found its way onto our &lt;a href=&#34;/thank-you/&#34;&gt;thank you page&lt;/a&gt;
   and into an appropriate page within the app itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of the week was business-as-usual. We sent out over 1000
invitations to &lt;a href=&#34;/roadmap/&#34;&gt;the Mailpile community site&lt;/a&gt;, continued
discussions with potential financial backers and related projects and
created &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/HoiPoi/issues&#34;&gt;a couple of detailed task descriptions on the Hoi Poi
bug-tracker&lt;/a&gt;, in case
friendly coders want to help improve the community site faster than
I&#39;ll be able to do on my own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the tech front, I implemented a &#34;Save this search&#34; feature, which
exposes some of the back-end&#39;s automated mail filter functionality in
a (hopefully!) user-friendly way. I also made progress on the actual
roadmap tasks- the VFS and the ability to browse the contents of a
mailbox (local or remote) without having to add it to the search index
first. These are still works in progress and have not been pushed up
to github yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Plans for this week&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Send out the rest of the invitations to community site&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revisit the settings of our Twitter and Facebook accounts. Should we
   even have a Facebook account?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep on hacking...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2015 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Digging for Data</title>
    <link>http://www.mailpile.is/blog/2015-05-18_Digging_for_Data.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week mostly went according to plan: backers e-mails were found,
invitations were sent, VFS work commenced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not quite as many invitations got sent out as I had hoped though,
because I was overcome by a debilitating bout of productive
procrastination. Inspired by the need to compile a list of backers on
the one hand, and a desire to refresh my memory on front-end development
work on the other, I ended up creating a new plugin that makes it easy
to run custom data mining operations on your own e-mail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what the result looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/files/2015-05-Datadig-Demo.jpg&#34; border=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The text is all blurry, because data is being extracted so fast it
makes your head spin! Right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you follow the S-shaped path of the green arrows, starting in the
upper right-hand corner, the tool works like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search and select messages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click the grid icon (top-right arrow)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add columns describing the desired data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click the Preview button to see if it works&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download the results as a CSV file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Profit!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to extract information which has already been defined as one
of the built-in recipes, this kind of personal data-mining becomes a
mere matter of pointing and clicking (the rows of the &lt;em&gt;Data Source&lt;/em&gt;
table are clickable). If the pre-existing recipes do not suffice, clever
geeks can search for virtually anything by using regular expressions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, over time, Mailpile community members will create and share
recipes for common things like invoice amounts or flight itineraries,
bank statements or stock market alerts... if you&#39;ve ever wanted to graph
the frequency of your Twitter mentions, this plugin (combined with any
old spreadsheet application) makes that easy to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plugin is named &lt;strong&gt;Datadig&lt;/strong&gt;, and to give it a try you will need to
pull the latest Mailpile from Github and run the following command on
the Mailpile CLI, &lt;code&gt;mailpile&amp;gt; plugins/load datadig&lt;/code&gt; - and yes, a GUI for
this is in the works.  Quit Mailpile, restart and the Datadig grid icon
should now appear whenever you select messages!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems only fitting that Mailpile will not only protect privacy, but
will also help people datamine their own e-mail for their own personal
benefit. The tabular spreadsheet format is universal and widely
understood, making this sort of thing potentially useful to a very wide
audience - not just hackers and coders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who would have thought CSV files could be so exciting?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code lives in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mailpile/Mailpile/tree/master/mailpile/contrib/datadig&#34;&gt;.../mailpile/contrib/datadig/&lt;/a&gt;
and I look forward to your pull requests. ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other news...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Plans for this week&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continue sending out invitations to &lt;a href=&#34;/roadmap/&#34;&gt;the voting page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More work on the VFS layer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take part in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/L10nLab/status/597827047654842369&#34;&gt;Localization Lab&#39;s 2nd
   AMA&lt;/a&gt;,
   this Thursday!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mystery meetings with mysterious people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2015 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Site updates and community roadmap launched</title>
    <link>http://www.mailpile.is/blog/2015-05-11_Weekly_Report.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the weekly report!  I&#39;m changing the format ever so slightly to
ensure the headlines displayed on the front-page and in compact RSS
readers are more informative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Done last week&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Updated the public website. The &lt;a href=&#34;/faq/&#34;&gt;FAQ&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;/&#34;&gt;front-page&lt;/a&gt; content
   was reviewed, updated and cleaned up. Individual &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; posts now
   have &#34;next&#34; and &#34;previous&#34; links. Minor tweaks were made to the site
   design to help with navigation of large pages: an up arrow in the lower
   right corner and a table-of-contents overview of the FAQ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unveiled &lt;a href=&#34;/roadmap/&#34;&gt;the Community Roadmap&lt;/a&gt;; votable content includes
   the licensing question and the post-1.0 roadmap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Published &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2015-05-08_Choosing_a_License.html&#34;&gt;a detailed blog-post explaining the AGPLv3 vs. Apache licensing
   question&lt;/a&gt; we need to resolve,
   publicized on Twitter and Hacker News. Took part in discussions on both
   venues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Plans for this week&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compile an up-to-date list of backers and their e-mail addresses, for
   sending out invitations to the community voting page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Send out the first 750 invitations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to coding: Key discovery front-end and VFS work are next!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2015 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Choosing a License for Mailpile 1.0</title>
    <link>http://www.mailpile.is/blog/2015-05-08_Choosing_a_License.html</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Mailpile backers and supporters!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The time has come for us to make a decision. Back when the project first
got off the ground, we had some difficulty deciding which Open Source
license we should use for our work. We narrowed it down to two licenses:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gnu.org/licenses/agpl-3.0.txt&#34;&gt;The GNU Affero General Public License,
    version 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0.html&#34;&gt;The Apache License, version
    2.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mailpile development code, the Alphas and the Betas have all been
released under &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; of these licenses. This was a legal hack to avoid
having to choose right away, without having to ask contributors to sign
copyright waivers before sharing code with the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, before the 1.0, we need to make a decision and settle upon one
license or the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have decided to let our community decide, and are in the process of
sending out invitations to &lt;a href=&#34;/roadmap/&#34;&gt;our community governance page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why do licenses matter?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although a bit boring, licensing is actually very important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The license is what grants exemptions from the rule of international
copyright law. Without a free and open license, our backers would not be
guaranteed the right to download, use, modify and share the results of
our work - the work they paid for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The license also helps define the community around the software, and
this is where things get tricky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some licenses, especially those championed by our friends at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fsf.org/&#34;&gt;Free
Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, are designed to protect the
rights of the end-user and ensure that community efforts remain with the
community. The AGPLv3 is the most modern and powerful such license,
designed for software like Mailpile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other licenses (such as the Apache license) are more permissive,
allowing corporations to make use of community code in traditional,
commercial software products. This fosters collaboration and motivates
companies to contribute valuable time and effort, but does so at the
expense of end-user freedom since many users of the software will end up
using proprietary derivitives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Permissive licensing: Webkit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An excellent example of permissive licensing, is the Webkit project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Webkit is based on KHTML, which was published under a relatively
permissive license (the GNU Lesser General Public License). I say
relatively permissive, because although the LGPL allows use within
proprietary products it does require that motifications to KHTML itself
be given back to the community. This balance allowed Apple to create
Safari, a proprietary browser, while forcing them to publish the engine
they derived from KHTML - an engine which we know today as Webkit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Webkit was then chosen by Google for use in their Chrome project, and
the rest is history: Webkit, daughter of KHTML and Apple, has taken the
lead as the world&#39;s fastest and most powerful HTML5 rendering engine. It
is now not only at the heart of both Safari and Chrome, but is used in a
wide range of other smaller browsers and open source projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a fantastic open source success story, and it&#39;s worth
remembering that this would probably never have happened if KHTML had
been licensed using a more permissive license, such as MIT, BSD or
Apache - those license would have allowed Apple to keep their
improvements to themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there are more lessons to be learned here!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today Safari and Chrome are both provided free of charge, but they are
proprietary programs and the community does not have access to their
inner workings. Amongst other things, this means &lt;strong&gt;the community cannot
easily inspect or audit&lt;/strong&gt; how and when these browsers &#34;phone home&#34; and
share private data with the companies that wrote them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can also be argued Webkit&#39;s license &lt;strong&gt;perpetuates the status quo&lt;/strong&gt;
and unfairly skews the market against truly free software. Compared with
these truly free alternatives, Chrome and Safari will always have a head
start because Google and Apple can keep some of their innovations to
themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course the counter-argument is, that without the motivation for big
companies to collaborate, Webkit probably wouldn&#39;t exist at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What about Mailpile?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although there are lessons to be learned, Mailpile is different from
Webkit. Webkit is a technical tool, one building block of many that
developers use when writing a browser. Mailpile on the other hand, is a
stand-alone end-user application, and (when it is finished) Mailpile can
be used directly to provide service online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Theoretically, a company could use Mailpile&#39;s code to build a service
which competes directly with GMail and Hotmail - but if Mailpile&#39;s
license does not require they share their changes, the users of these
competing services will be no more free than they were before. There is
also no guarantee that these companies will contribute to the community
version of Mailpile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, many companies (and some individuals) strongly
dislike the AGPL and avoid all software which uses it. These people will
be excluded from our community and will not help us improve Mailpile if
we use that license.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that becomes the crux of the question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do we want to compell companies to share their changes to our code,
which is what the AGPL does, or do we want to take a more trusting
approach and rely on enlightened self interest and good-will - by
releasing under the Apache license?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some, this is an idealogical question, a matter of &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; or
&lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt;. Is it morally acceptable to allow people to benefit from
Mailpile&#39;s work without contributing back? Is it morally acceptable for
Mailpile&#39;s authors to tie the hands of other businesses?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For others, this is merely a matter of strategy and tactics. What is
most likely to improve end-user freedom in the long run? What is most
likely to help Mailpile itself develop and thrive? Will chosing a
restrictive license marginalize the project and prevent us from
affecting wide-spread improvements to how people use e-mail? Will a
permissive license make it easier for abusive companies to launch new
webmail services as honey-pots to harvest and collect private e-mail
data?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those are the questions we need to answer!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have an opinion, one way or another, I encourage you to write
blog post explaining your position (or send links you feel are
relevant). If you prefer to publish yourself I&#39;ll be happy to link to
your website - or we can publish guest posts here on this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully a few people will express their opinions and help our
community &lt;a href=&#34;/roadmap/&#34;&gt;vote&lt;/a&gt; one way or another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2015 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  </item>
</channel></rss>