<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
  <title>Mailpile: Press releases</title>
  <link>http://www.mailpile.is/press/</link>
  <item>
    <title>Press release: Secure e-mail project raises $50,000 in one week</title>
    <link>http://www.mailpile.is/press/2013-08-09_50000_USD_in_one_week.html</link>
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;Mailpile, a secure e-mail software project, has raised over $50,000 USD
from 1200 individuals on the Indiegogo.com crowdfunding website, in just
under one week. The project's goal is to write software which will make
secure encryption of e-mail more user friendly and accessible to the
general public, in addition to providing a compelling open source
alternative to the centralized e-mail solutions offered by Google,
Microsoft and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project's focus on privacy and giving end users more control over
their e-mail data appears to have touched a nerve with the technical
community, in part due to the revelations of Edward Snowden and the
recent shuttering of the privacy focused Lavabit e-mail service. When
the project was first announced at the OHM 2013 technical festival in the
Netherlands last weekend, it was met with rounds of applause and a flurry
of activity on the Twitter social website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mailpile is the work of a small team of software developers based in
Reykjavík, Iceland. They hope to raise enough money to spend at least
two man-years on the project. Fund-raising will continue until September
10th, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For further information, see &lt;a href="http://igg.me/at/mailpile"&gt;http://igg.me/at/mailpile&lt;/a&gt; or contact
&lt;a href="m&amp;#97;&amp;#x69;&amp;#x6C;t&amp;#111;:&amp;#x74;&amp;#101;&amp;#x61;&amp;#x6D;&amp;#64;&amp;#x6D;&amp;#x61;&amp;#x69;lp&amp;#105;&amp;#x6C;&amp;#101;&amp;#x2E;&amp;#x69;&amp;#x73;"&gt;&amp;#x74;&amp;#101;&amp;#x61;&amp;#x6D;&amp;#64;&amp;#x6D;&amp;#x61;&amp;#x69;lp&amp;#105;&amp;#x6C;&amp;#101;&amp;#x2E;&amp;#x69;&amp;#x73;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;About the team&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bjarni Rúnar Einarsson is tech lead for the project. He has been been
working on various aspects of the Internet since the mid-90s, including 6 years
fighting spam and viruses and 3 years on Google's site reliability team (SRE).
Bjarni received the Nordic Free Software Award in 2010 for his contribution's
to Iceland's local tech community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brennan Novak is the team's user interface and user experience designer.
He has contracted for large companies like Nike and Intel as well as
smaller startups and open source projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smári McCarthy is the team's privacy and security expert. He has spent
the last few years working as the director of the International Modern
Media Institute, working with activists, NGOs and governments on
information security and network policy issues.&lt;/p&gt;
    </description>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Fréttatilkynning: Íslenskur sproti safnar 6 milljónum á einni viku</title>
    <link>http://www.mailpile.is/press/2013-08-09_50000_USD_a_einni_viku.html</link>
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;Mailpile er íslenskt hugbúnaðarverkefni sem hefur safnað yfir 6
milljónum króna ($50.000 bandaríkadollara) á innan við viku. Féð kemur
frá einstaklingum víðsvegar um heim sem hafa styrkt herferð á
fjáröflunarvefnum Indiegogo. Markmið verkefnisins er að skrifa hugbúnað
sem bætir friðhelgi einkalífs fólks á Netinu með því að einfalda notkun
dulritunar í tölvupósti. Verkefnið stefnir einnig að því að bjóða upp á
raunhæfan valkost við miðstýrð tölvupóstkerfi Google, Microsoft og
annarra bandarískra stórfyrirtækja.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Áherslur verkefnisins á friðhelgi einkalífs og að auka sjálfstæði fólks
sem notar tölvupóst hefur fallið í mjög góðan jarðveg hjá tölvunotendum
um allan heim, meðal annars vegna uppljóstrana Edwards Snowdens um
víðtækt eftirlit bandarísku öryggisstofnunarinnar með netnotkun
almennings. Verkefnið var kynnt við góðar undirtektir á OHM 2013
ráðstefnunni í Hollandi og fréttirnar fóru í framhaldinu sem eldur í
sinu um Twitter samræðuvefinn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mailpile er hugarfóstur tölvunarfærðingsins Bjarna Rúnars Einarssonar,
en honum til halds og trausts eru Smári McCarthy og Brennan Novak.
Hópurinn stefnir að því að safna $100.000 bandaríkjadollurum og nýta féð
til að fjármagna eins árs vinnu við þróun þess. Fjáröflun mun standa
yfir fram til 10. september, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nánari upplýsingar má finna á &lt;a href="http://igg.me/at/mailpile"&gt;http://igg.me/at/mailpile&lt;/a&gt;, með
tölvupósti til &lt;a href="&amp;#x6D;&amp;#x61;&amp;#x69;&amp;#x6C;&amp;#x74;&amp;#x6F;:&amp;#x74;&amp;#101;&amp;#x61;&amp;#x6D;&amp;#64;&amp;#x6D;&amp;#x61;&amp;#x69;&amp;#x6C;p&amp;#105;l&amp;#101;&amp;#x2E;&amp;#105;&amp;#x73;"&gt;&amp;#x74;&amp;#101;&amp;#x61;&amp;#x6D;&amp;#64;&amp;#x6D;&amp;#x61;&amp;#x69;&amp;#x6C;p&amp;#105;l&amp;#101;&amp;#x2E;&amp;#105;&amp;#x73;&lt;/a&gt; eða í síma Bjarna, 6900409.&lt;/p&gt;
    </description>
  </item>
</channel></rss>
